Guide to the James and Eugenia Zilboorg Papers
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
James and Eugenia Zilboorg papers
1898-1972
YCAL MSS 259
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
5.22
(10 boxes)
The James and Eugenia Zilboorg Papers consist of family correspondence, business correspondence, other personal papers, photographs and printed material documenting the life of James and Eugenia Zilboorg and their families. The two largest groups of letters are between James and Eugenia Zilboorg and between the Zilboorgs and the Gel'fman family. In addition to these two large groups of correspondence, there are letters from other family members and friends, including the Zil'burg family of Kiev. Of particular interest is James' early correspondence with his brother Gregory Zilboorg, who served as a Minister in the governments of Aleksandr Kerenskii and Georgii L'vov before emigrating to the United States and becoming a psychoanalyst and historian of psychiatry. The collection also contains one box of printed material related to revolutionary Russian politics (1898-1927) and one box of other papers which include family photographs, ephemera and collected documents relating to revolutionary Russian politics.
Zilboorg, James
Zilboorg, Eugenia
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Natalie Fiess,1992.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Associated Materials
Gregory Zilboorg Papers, YCAL MSS 258
James and Eugenia Zilboorg
James Zilboorg was born Jakov Movshevich Zil'burg in Kiev, September 3, 1892. Eugenia Zilboorg was born Evgenia Minaevna Gel'fman in Kiev in the 1890s. James emigrated to the U.S. in 1914 and Eugenia followed in 1915. They became American citizens but lived for many years in Mexico. Several of James and Eugenia's family members also emigrated from Kiev, going to Denmark, France, Danzig, Palestine, New York and joining them in Mexico.
The Gel'fman name is also spelled Gelfman, Helfman and Helfmann. The Zil'burg name is Americanized as Zilboorg.
In 1914 James began a lifelong career in engineering working for Westinghouse Corporation in Pittsburgh. He later worked for their international subsidary in Mexico and for other international and Mexican companies in the electrical power industry. In 1961 James retired and the couple moved to Long Island, where James died in 1968.
Menashe Khaimovich Gel'fman, Eugenia's father, ran export and trade businesses in Kiev and Danzig, dealing in such products as flour, sugar, tobacco and wine. Eugenia's siblings include Minia (who emigrated to France and married a woman named Evgenia), Emma Andersen (who emigrated to Denmark and married Kai Andersen), IUzia (who emigrated to Haifa, Palestine and eventually to New York and married a woman named Hilda), Sofia Spektareva (who remained in Russia and worked in education), Vera (who lived with the Zilboorgs in Mexico before marrying Oleg Saitcevitsky) and Liza.
James's parents, Moshe M. Zil'burg and wife, also emigrated to Mexico and lived in Mexico City. Siblings of James include Esther Levitas (who emigrated to Mexico and married Solomon Levitas), Gregory (who emigrated to New York and became a notable scholar of psychoanalysis) and Basia Osherov. For further details about the life and work of Gregory Zilboorg, readers may consult the Gregory Zilboorg Papers, YCAL MSS 258.
James and Eugenia Zilboorg had three daughters: Natalie Fiess, Olga Irvine and Lydia Cato.
Scope and Contents
The James and Eugenia Zilboorg Papers document the experience of a middle class Jewish family in Kiev that emigrates to the United States, Mexico and Palestine. The papers consist of family correspondence, business correspondence, other personal papers, photographs and printed material documenting the life of James and Eugenia Zilboorg and their families. The two largest groups of letters are between James and Eugenia Zilboorg and between the Zilboorgs and the Gel'fman family.
Letters between James and Eugenia Zilboorg document their life together including the details of their emigration from Kiev and the management of their family affairs. James often traveled on business and many of his letters were written during these travels. The letters are addressed not only to Eugenia, but to their daughters and to Eugenia's sister Vera and mother.
Letters between the Zilboorgs and the Gel'fman family document the details of the lives of Gel'fman and Zilboorg family members. They provide details about the families' struggle to thrive during and after the Russian revolutionary period, emigrate, and begin new lives abroad. The families strove to maintain a daily intimacy through their correspondence and their letters provide a personal record of the Jewish emigration experience in the early twentieth century. They also include details of the various businesses that the Gel'fman family managed.
In addition to these two large groups of correspondence, there are letters from other family members and friends, including the Zil'burg family of Kiev. Of particular interest is James' early correspondence with his brother Gregory. Gregory struggled to continue his education during the Revolution and in 1917 served as secretary to the Minister of Labor in the governments of Georgii L'vov and Aleksandr Kerenskii.
Besides correspondence, the collection contains one box of printed material related to revolutionary Russian politics (1898-1927) and one box of other papers which include family photographs, ephemera and collected documents relating to revolutionary Russian politics.
Arrangement
The collection is organized into three series: Correspondence, Other Papers, and Printed Material.
Emigration and immigration -- Mexico; Emigration and immigration -- Russia; Jewish diaspora; Soviet Union -- History -- Revolution, 1917-1921; Photographs; Zilboorg, Eugenia; Zilboorg, Gregory, 1890-1959; Zilboorg, James; Gel'fman family; Zil'burg family
- Correspondence, circa 1910-1972; Series I; 2.92; (7 boxes)
  Arrangement
  The series is organized into two subseries: Family correspondence and Business correspondence. Family correspondence is arranged alphabetically. Business correspondence is arranged chronologically.
  Scope and Contents
  Family correspondence documents the lives of the Zilboorg and Gel'fman families. Most of the letters date from 1913 to 1940. Almost all of the letters filed under James Zilboorg are addressed to Eugenia Zilboorg and vice versa.
  Business correspondence relates to James Zilboorg's personal business. Topics addressed include job applications, letters of recommendation and James's resume.
  A few letters are accompanied by English translations, as noted in folder notes. The translations are by an unknown person (possibly Natalie Fiess or another member of the Zilboorg family) in the 1990s.
  Third party correspondence related to Russian revolutionary politics and collected by James and Eugenia is filed in Other Papers.
  - Family Correspondence
    - "A" general, 1914-1948 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Anderson, Emma (née Gel'fman) and Kai, 1921-1971, undated (Box 1, Folder 2)
      Related Archival Materials note
      See also: Gel'fman family and Gel'fman family
    - Bashkirov, K., undated (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Bass, Samuel and Lisa, 1931-1954 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Beizman, Boris IA., 1914-1934 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Braunstein, David, 1910s, 1927, undated (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Breslow, Sylvia (née Sherman), 1914-1924 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Brylowicz, Stanislaw, 1924-1925 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - El', Aleksandr, 1914-1915 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - l'Etienne, Margarita, 1922 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Fiess, Natalie (née Zilboorg) and Olga Irvine (née Zilboorg), 1942-1943 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Fiess, Natalie (née Zilboorg) and Edward, 1942-1947 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - "G" general, 1920, 1930 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Gelf'man, IUzia, 1910s-1935, undated (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - Gel'fman, Liza, 1916, undated (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - Gel'fman, Minia and Evgenia, 1923-1971 (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - Gel'fman family, 1910s-1919 (Box 1, Folder 17-24)
    - Gel'fman family, 1920s-1936, undated (Box 2, Folder 25-33)
    - "H" general, 1915, 1920 (Box 2, Folder 34)
    - Irvine, Olga (née Zilboorg), 1946-1946 (Box 2, Folder 35)
    - "K" general, 1932, 1938, undated (Box 2, Folder 36)
    - "L" general, 1913-1930 (Box 2, Folder 37)
    - Lahm, Polina, 1941-1943, undated (Box 2, Folder 38)
    - Levee, Irina (née Gel'fman) and Lazar', 1923-1925, undated (Box 2, Folder 39)
    - Levitas, Esther (née Zil'burg) and Solomon, 1913-1937, undated (Box 2, Folder 40)
      See also: Zil'burg family
    - Lichtenshtein, Nadia and Izakil', 1933-1947 (Box 2, Folder 41)
    - "M" general, 1912-1966 (Box 2, Folder 42)
    - Nisenbaum, Fishel', 1922 (Box 2, Folder 43)
    - Osherov, Basia (née Zil'burg), 1914-1922, undated (Box 2, Folder 44)
      See also:Zil'burg family
    - "P" general, undated (Box 3, Folder 45)
    - "R" general, 1911-1927 (Box 3, Folder 46)
    - Rosaler, Jean and Akim, 1921-1927 (Box 3, Folder 47)
    - "S" general, 1917-1923 (Box 3, Folder 48)
    - Saitcevsky, Oleg, 1931-1942 (Box 3, Folder 49)
    - Saitcevsky, Vera (née Gel'fman) and Oleg, 1922-1942, undated (Box 3, Folder 50-59)
      Includes some letters to James and Eugenia Zilboorg from their children
    - Sherman, Belle, 1916 (Box 3, Folder 60)
    - Sherman, Lillian, 1914-1916, undated (Box 3, Folder 61)
    - Spektareva, Sofia (née Gel'fman), 1915-1972, undated (Box 3, Folder 62-63)
    - "T" general, 1913, undated (Box 3, Folder 64)
    - Theiss, George, 1913-1914 (Box 3, Folder 65)
    - "V" general, 1919, 1930s (Box 3, Folder 66)
    - Wousild, Frieda, 1915 (Box 3, Folder 67)
    - Zaitsevskii, M. and N., 1932-1937 (Box 3, Folder 68)
    - Zilboorg, Carolyn, undated (Box 3, Folder 69)
    - Zilboorg, Eugenia, 1913-1944 (Box 4, Folder 70-82)
    - Zilboorg, Eugenia, undated (1940s) (Box 5, Folder 83)
    - Zilboorg, Eugenia, undated (Box 5, Folder 84)
    - Zilboorg, Eugenia, outgoing to Gel'fman family and to Boria, 1916-1918 (Box 5, Folder 85)
    - Zilboorg, Gregory, incoming and outgoing, 1915-1959 (Box 5, Folder 86-92)
    - Zilboorg, James, 1914-1922 (Box 5, Folder 93-97)
    - Zilboorg, James, 1923-1947 (Box 6, Folder 98-109)
      Includes one letter to Vera and Oleg Saitcevsky, 1942
    - Zilboorg, James, undated (1920s) (Box 6, Folder 110)
    - Zilboorg, James, undated (1930s) (Box 7, Folder 111)
    - Zilboorg, James, undated (1940s) (Box 7, Folder 112)
    - Zilboorg, James, undated (Box 7, Folder 113-114)
    - Zilboorg, James, outgoing to Irina, Evelyn and Zil'burg family, 1916, 1921, undated (Box 7, Folder 115)
    - Zil'burg family, 1914-1931 (Box 7, Folder 116)
    - General correspondence identified by first name only, A-Z, 1913-1954, undated (Box 7, Folder 117)
    - _____, Liuba, 1965, undated (Box 7, Folder 118)
    - _____, Liza, 1915-1923 (Box 7, Folder 119)
    - _____, Sarra, undated (Box 7, Folder 120)
    - _____, Volodia, 1918 (Box 7, Folder 121)
    - _____, Volodia, 1929-1940 (Box 7, Folder 122)
    - Letters with illegible signatures, 1914-1942, undated (Box 7, Folder 123)
      Arranged chronologically
    - Unsigned letters, 1915-1924, undated (Box 7, Folder 124)
      Several of these letters are incomplete
    - Invitations, announcements and calling cards, 1949, 1954, undated (Box 7, Folder 125)
    - Unaddressed postcards, undated (Box 7, Folder 126)
    - Envelopes, 1923, 1925, undated (Box 7, Folder 127)
    - Notes, undated (Box 7, Folder 128)
      Includes brief notes which could not be associated with a particular letter and notes on Zilboorg family history
  - Business Correspondence, 1914-1966
    - Zilboorg, Eugenia, letters of recommendation, 1918, 1920 (Box 7, Folder 129)
    - Zilboorg, James, 1914-1966 (Box 7, Folder 130)
      Arranged chronologically; some letters are bound into reverse-chronological packets
      A job application to the Tenessee Valley Authority, 1939, includes a photograph of James Zilboorg
- Other Papers, 1898-1968; Series II; 0.21; (1 box)
  Series II is arranged chronologically.
  Other papers include educational records, ephemera, photographs, personal papers and newspaper clippings. Also included is a collection of documents related to the politics of the Russian revolutionary period, which includes some third party correspondence.
  - Bank notes from Russia, Finland and Germany, 1898-1922 (Box 8, Folder 131)
  - Educational records of James Zilboorg, 1908-1914 (Box 8, Folder 132)
  - Educational records of Eugenia Zilboorg, 1910, 1920 (Box 8, Folder 133)
  - Lesson book of Eugenia Zilboorg, 1911-1912 (Box 8, Folder 134)
  - "Political action"
    - Poster, "Den' kolosa rzhi [Day of the sheaf of rye]", 1912 March 6
    - Cablegram announcing the abdication of Tsar Nicholas II, copy, 1917 8/21 March (Box 8, Folder 135)
    - Cablegrams to President Kerenskii, copies, [1917] (Box 8, Folder 136)
      One cablegram is accompanied by an English translation
    - Third party correspondence related to George V. Lomonosoff, 1918 (Box 8, Folder 137)
    - Correspondence related to a letter to the editor of Russkoe Slovo, 1919 (Box 8, Folder 138)
    - Third party correspondence related to Russian Ambassador Boris Bakhmetev, 1919 (Box 8, Folder 139)
    - Correspondence related to Russian income tax law, 1910s (Box 8, Folder 140)
    - Other papers and one clipping relating to Russian Revolutionary politics, 1910s (Box 8, Folder 141)
  - Family photographs, 1914-1943, undated (Box 8, Folder 142)
  - Sketch of a baby, in pencil, probably by James Zilboorg, 1922 (Box 8, Folder 143)
  - Newspaper clippings, 1939, 1944, undated (Box 8, Folder 144)
    Includes "Fortælling fra den russiske Revolution," an article in Danish by Kai Andersen.
  - Russian grammar notes, 1944 (Box 8, Folder 145)
  - Concert programs, 1951, undated (Box 8, Folder 146)
  - Obituary notices of James Zilboorg, 1968 (Box 8, Folder 147)
- Printed Material, 1899-1923; Series III; 0.42; (1 box)
  Series II is organized into two Subseries: Serials and Monographs. Both are arranged alphabetically by title of work.
  Printed material relates to the politics of the Russian revolutionary period. A few of the monographs are incomplete.
  - Serials
    - Nakanune. London. Issues 1-12., 1899 (Box 9, Folder 148)
    - Nakanune. London. Issues 13-16, 19, 21, 22, 24., 1900 (Box 9, Folder 149)
    - Revoliutsionnaia Rossia. Issues 20 and 25., 1903 (Box 9, Folder 150)
    - Revoliutsionnaia Rossia. Issues 43, 48, 51, 53, 55-57., 1904 (Box 9, Folder 151)
    - Revoliutsionnaia Rossia. Paris. Issues 58, 60, 61, 65, 67, 68, 71-75., 1905 (Box 9, Folder 152)
    - Sotsialisticheskii Vestnik. Berlin. Issue 8-9., 1923 (Box 9, Folder 153)
  - Monographs
    - La Révolution Russe et la Paix, undated (Box 9, Folder 154)
      This volume does not have a cover or title page
    - Sovety i Sovetskaia Vlast' v Rosii, by K.M. Oberuchev. New York: Knigoizdatel'stvo Narodopravstvo., 1919 (Box 9, Folder 155)
    - Sovremennyi Moment v Otsenke Partii Sotsialistov-Revoliutsionerov. Paris., 1919 (Box 9, Folder 156)
    - Sushchnost' Sotsializma, by A. Shefle with commentary by P. Lavrov. Published by Vl. Raspopov., 1906 (Box 9, Folder 157)
    - Untitled, heading on first page reads "Novye Politicheskie Protsessy", undated (Box 9, Folder 158)
- Oversize, 2.08; (1 box)
  - Poster, "Den' kolosa rzhi [Day of the sheaf of rye]" (Series III), 1912 March 6 (Box 10, Folder 159)
  - Newspaper clippings (Series III), 1939 (Box 10, Folder 160)